Guide to the Isaac Hicks Papers 1791-1820 MS 297
New-York Historical Society
Isaac Hicks papers
1791-1820
1791-1806
New-York Historical Society
Hicks, Isaac, 1767-1820
MS 297
35 Linear feet
Isaac Hicks was a Quaker merchant, born in 1767 and active in the mercantile and shipping business from 1790-1807, both by himself and in partnerships. The collection includes predominantly business papers, but also includes a handful of non-business related documents. Approximately half of the collection is correspondence, and half of the collection is business documents. The correspondence is primarily in regards to the sale and shipment of goods and the procurement of insurance policies. The business documents include but are not limited to checks, insurance policies, bills, bonds, and more.
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series I-Correspondence: Letters and letter books, as well as the 1950's summary of letters
Series II-Business Documents: This series includes bills, bills of exchange, memorandum books, and ledgers; prices current; shipping papers (including papers organized for specific ships); promissory notes, orders to pay, and protest notes; invoices; insurance policies; and miscellaneous business documents.
Series III-Non-business documents: Any non-business documents, including financial records from the African Free School.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection predominantly contains materials from the business ventures of Isaac Hicks and the various companies that he associated with over the course of his career. Included are:
•a large collection of letters to and from ship captains, owners, and other business associates of Hicks regarding shipping, cargo, prices, and more
•Letters relating to Power of Attorney, allowing Hicks to buy and sell on behalf of other merchants
•Promissory notes regarding credit and payments
•Insurance policies for ships and captains that Hicks had contracts with
•Prices Current, listing the current market value range of a variety of dry goods and whaling materials
•Bound Ledgers
•Bound Memorandum books-which allowed Hicks to keep a record of credits and debits before they were officially entered into the Ledger
•Receipt Books
•Assorted Business documents, and more.
Also included are a collection of letters from associates of Hicks after his death, and a summary of letters received, created around the mid 1950's to early 1960's. This collection does not include a substantial amount of personal correspondence, if any, and relates almost completely to Hicks's business ventures.
Biographical/Historical Note
Isaac Hicks was born in 1767, into the Quaker farming community of Westbury, Long Island. He was the son of Samuel and Phebe (nee Seamen), and had a prominent extended family within the Quaker community which included Quaker minister Elias Hicks (1748-1830) and artist Edward Hicks (1780-1849). While in Westbury, Hicks worked both as a tailor and as a teacher. In 1789, disillusioned with teaching, Hicks moved to New York City: he opened a mercantile shop under the title of "grocer." That year, he also met Sara Doughty (1768-1847). They married in 1790 and had six children: John, Robert, Benjamin, Isaac, Elizabeth, and Mary.
In 1790, Hicks began a series of partnerships; first with Richard Loines; then with Richard Loines, his father William Loines, and William Loines's brother-in-law, John Alsop, Jr. Loines, Alsop, & Company specialized in importing British made dry goods, and it is within these partnerships that Hicks transitioned from the title 'grocer' to 'dry-goods specialist.' It is also with Loines, Alsop & Co. that Hicks learned how to supplement his income, as the partnership owned a wharf, rented business properties, and were co-owners of a mill, all to bring in additional income during the slow seasons of their business.
In 1791, Loines, Alsop & Company dissolved. William Loines retired, Richard Loines joined with his brother John to create their own mercantile business, and Hicks and John Alsop, Jr. continued their partnership under the new name of Alsop & Hicks. It was at this point that the pair began being seen in directories under the listing of 'merchant.' For three years, Alsop & Hicks continued acting as an international importer of dry goods. In 1794, after not making the money they expected and having trouble collecting on debts owed to them, the company Alsop & Hicks changed direction from 'dry-goods specialists' to 'shipping and commission agents.'
This change allowed Alsop & Hicks to act as trusted agents for other merchants, selling goods that were sent to them rather than buying and selling on their own. The firm also helped merchants and captains outfit ships, purchase insurance, and obtain cargo. It was in this venture that Hicks's relationships within the Quaker community were beneficial: Quaker merchants were more likely to trust other Quakers and their families with their goods than they would an outsider. In May of 1794, John Alsop, Jr. left New York City for a quieter life in Hudson, New York, though he did continue to maintain part interest in the firm and bring in customers from the Hudson area, including: Thomas Jenkins & Sons, Seth Jenkins, and the Paddock family, among others. It is these connections that also allowed Alsop & Hicks to gain commissions in Nantucket and New Bedford, Massachusetts, as well as continuing earlier commissions of cotton, tobacco, and rice, out of Savannah, Georgia. After continuing business in this manner for a number of years, Hicks dissolved his partnership with John Alsop, Jr. and formed a partnership with Benjamin D. Doughty-longtime clerk of Alsop & Hicks. However, a yellow fever outbreak led to the death of Benjamin Doughty shortly after this partnership began, and Hicks refrained from creating new partnerships through his retirement.
Now that Hicks was on his own, while continuing to do business in the same manner as he did while part of Alsop & Hicks, Isaac Hicks began focusing more of his efforts towards increasing his sale of whale products-especially oil and spermaceti candles. These commissions made up the majority of his revenue until 1800. Hicks was able to increase and keep his trade contacts in the whaling market by being fastidious in attempting to regulate the fluctuating prices of whale oil, even when it was at the loss of a commission. He also attempted to restore some of the former marketing practices of spermaceti candle maker's in order to increase the candle makers profits.
By 1800, Hicks commissions from whale merchants began a steady decline-mostly because of the changing circumstances within the whaling industry, as well as some decisions made by Hicks. Insurance rates were rising, the number of whales was dwindling in the Atlantic, and Hicks allowed his brother, Samuel, to take over many of his commissions when Samuel began his own business. Also, with the falling prices, captains and owners were becoming unhappy with their lack of income, and blamed the problems on Hicks. Because of the dwindling income from whale products, Hicks returned his focus to other forms of shipping and commission.
By 1802, Hicks began considering at least partial retirement from business, as he was beginning to get notices of declining health. It was because of this, that in December 1802, Hicks, along with others in a syndicate, purchased the ship Thames in order to capitalize on trade to St. Petersburg, Russia and quickly increase their earnings. When all was said and done, Hicks made a handsome profit-grossing nearly $14,000 ($292,611.21 in 2018). After a time, Hicks and his syndicate sold the Thames, and yet while Hicks continued to put on excursions to the Black Sea, none were as profitable. Regardless, by 1805, Hicks left New York City to return to Westbury and by 1807 had officially retired from business at the age of 38.
Throughout Hicks's career, he was a staunch abolitionist and active in the Quaker Meeting. He was a member of an anti-slavery organization that mixed both Friends and prominent non-Quakers, as well as a member of the New York Manumission Society. As part of this society, he was a fund-raiser for the African Free School, and while these might have been a small distraction during his career, it became all-consuming after Hicks entered retirement.
Isaac Hicks was also extremely active in the Quaker Meeting, acting on multiple committees. In 1816, he was nominated for Clerk of the Westbury Meeting. He was also well known in many other Quaker circles outside of the Meeting, mostly thanks to his cousin, Elias Hicks, who Isaac traveled extensively with. Hicks also worked closely with his cousin, Edward Hicks, in an attempt to bring him back to preaching and away from painting by paying off his debts. After an active and varied retirement, Hicks fell ill on January 10, 1820, and died shortly thereafter at 52 years old.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was acquired predominately by donation by Marietta Hicks in 1958, but some of the collection was acquired at auction in approximately 1979.
Business papers; Business records.; Cotton trade -- New York (State) -- New York.; Insurance, Marine -- New York (State) -- New York.; Jamaica -- Commerce.; Liverpool (England) -- Commerce.; New York (N.Y.) -- Commerce.; Savannah (Ga.); Quakers; Seizure of vessels and cargoes; Ships -- Cargo; Ships -- New York (State) -- New York.; Shipping -- New York (State) -- New York.; Shipping -- United States.; Tobacco -- United States.; West Indies -- Commerce.; whaling; Alsop, John, 1753-1832; Doughty, Benjamin, 1790-1796; Forbes, Edward, 1791-1820; Hicks, Isaac, 1767-1820; Hicks, Sarah, 1768-1847; Paddock, Daniel; Bank of New York; Bank of the United States (1791-1811); Manhattan Company; Merchants' Bank (New York, N.Y.); New York Insurance Company; Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan; Thomas Jenkins and Sons; United Insurance Company
- Series I: Correspondence, 1791-1806; 18 Linear feet
  Arrangement Note
  Correspondence in this series is organized by year, and then alphabetically by surname of the correspondent. Exceptions to this are specifically noted in the folder list. While the correspondence is organized by year into folders, it is important to note that the correspondence is not always chronological within the folders themselves. It is unknown how the correspondence was originally arranged by Hicks, as it was subsequently re-foldered.
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series contains correspondence between Isaac Hicks; Alsop & Hicks; or Hicks & Doughty and their clients. Main topics include payment for goods provided, payment of debt to Alsop & Hicks, and requests for third parties to be paid; as well as requests for goods. Interspersed throughout this series are a number of loose invoices or records of debts and credits.
  Recurring correspondents include, but are not limited to, Thomas Jenkins & Sons; Gardner & Swain; Daniel Paddock; and multiple individuals with the surname "Coffin". Some of the correspondence are to these individuals as clients, and other as captains of the many ships that Hicks used to transport the goods that he sold.
  The series includes correspondence predominantly from the east coast of the United States, especially Hudson, New York; Newport, Rhode Island; Savannah, Georgia; New Bedford, Massachusetts; Boston, Massachusetts; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Baltimore, Maryland; and Nantucket, Massachusetts. There is also correspondence from Europe and the Carribbean, especially London, England; Liverpool, England; Derry, Ireland; Dublin, Ireland; Cork, Ireland; the West Indies, and Amsterdam, Netherlands.
  While most of the correspondence relates to business matters such as the shipping of goods, prices for goods, and the sale of goods, among other things, other topics are also included in the correspondence. However, there is also correspondence about social, political, and economic issues. These include how European wars impact the global market, changing political ideologies in Great Britain and Ireland, piracy, and the changing global economy.
  Interspersed throughout the series are letters in French, Spanish, and Dutch. While some are mentioned, most are not.
  Correspondent names and ship names are noted when they appear three times or more within a folder.
  - Summary of Letters, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    This folder contains notes and statistics regarding the correspondence in this collection. It includes such details as the number of Quaker vs. non-Quaker correspondants, the geographical makeup of the correspondents, and lists of correspondents, dates, and topics. It is unknown who created this file, when it was created, or how accurate the statistics are.
  - Letters: 1791-1793 (Box -)
    - Letters: J-Z, 1791 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      This folder includes frequent correspondence from Thomas Jenkins & Sons, and Daniel Paddock, as well as many other individuals from areas such as Hudson, New York; Savannah, Georgia; and Newport, Rhode Island. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods, payment of debt, and the procurement of insurance policies. Caleb Smith discusses leaving town because he feared imprisonment for owing debts.
    - Letters: A-G, 1792 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      This folder contains a significant amount of correspondence with a John Church, as well as a number of other individuals. Most of the correspondence is in regards to the sale of dry goods and other financial matters.
      Ships Mentioned:Thomas
    - Letters: H-K, 1792 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including Thomas Jenkins & Sons, Jonathan Jenkins, John Jauncey, and George Kelly. The correspondence primarily discusses the shipment and sale of dry goods, and the settling of accounts. Some letters include the request to deliver funds to Hicks's old partners, James & Richard Loines, as well as George Kelly informing Hicks that Hicks's goods came too late in the season and so they will be held until the next season instead of being sold upon arrival.
      Ships Mentioned:Experiment, Thomas
    - Letters: L-W, 1792 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including William Lindy, Shadrach Till, and Peter Voorhees. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to normal business matters. Other correspondence includes a letter by Caleb Smith, who appears to be asking Hicks to forgive his debt due to the fact that he can not pay it. He pleads for Hicks to think of his wife and children, and how they would not be able to survive. A letter by Benjamin Stratton, Jr. mentions 'next month's meeting', in regards to the Society of Friends. Another letter was sent to inform Hicks that goods had not been sent because the current market price was too low.
      Ships Mentioned:Alex, Eliza,
    - Letters: A-W, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including Robert Bulton, William Lamb, Seth Jenkins & Sons, Caleb Smith, and Cornelius Wing. The correspondence primarily discusses the shipment and sale of dry goods, and the settling of accounts.
      Multiple letters from Caleb Smith discuss him paying off his debts to Alsop & Hicks. A letter from Benjamin Huntting discusses how the 'indians' that he was going to use to load his ship would not assist him, so he was going to be unable to properly staff his ship. There are also multiple letters and an invoice from Robert Bolton of Savannah, Georgia, mainly regarding the shipping of tobacco and rice.
  - Letters: 1794-1796 (Box -)
    - Letters: A-B, 1794 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including Joseph Anthony, Jonathan Arnold, and Enoch Barnard. The correspondence is primarily in regards to shipping and finances.
      Ships Mentioned:Hero
    - Letters: C-F, 1794 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including Micajah Coffin & Sons, and Samuel Coates. The correspondence is primarily in regards to shipping and finances. One letter asks Hicks for an extension of a due-date, by informing Hicks that due to unforeseen circumstances, the money was not available that month, but will definitely be available by next month. A majority of the other letters are asking Alsop & Hicks to buy or sell goods on behalf of the clients.
    - Letters: G-H, 1794 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including Gilbert Gardner & Co, Gardner & Swain, Gotton Gelston, E. Goodrich, and HS Howland Jr.. Most correspondence is in regards to normal business dealings-buying and selling goods and paying debts. One letter from Gilbert Gardner & Co. requests that Alsop & Hicks first use the money from the sale of Gardner & Co's goods to settle their debt before sending the remaining proceeds to Gardner. Another letter from John Hutchenson talks about Hutchenson being arrested and subsequently making bail.
      Ships Mentioned: Ranger
    - Letters: J-L, 1794 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including John Jauncey, Jonathan Jenkins, Seth Jenkins & Sons, and Thomas Jenkins & Sons. John Jauncey discusses how he still can not pay his debt but he should be able to soon. Jonathan Jenkins makes up a large portion of the correspondence. One particular letter discusses a petition to congress to repeal a patent letter, and another letter asks Alsop & Hicks to ship a very long list of fabrics. Seth Jenkins & Sons writes to ask about Alsop & Hicks procuring insurance for the ship, Mohawk. Lastly, Thomas Jenkins & Sons writes that they are looking for crewhands, and requests a list of goods be sent, including sugar, beef, pork, and turpentine.
    - Letters: M-R, 1794 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clilents, including John McLeod, Francis Macy, Daniel Paddock, and Judah Paddock. Most of the letters are in regards to people making payments to Alsop & Hicks.
      A letter from John McLeod discusses how Algerines were capturing vessels, causing merchants to have problems selling goods and being nervous to send more. He also discusses a smallpox outbreak. Francis Macy discusses a trade embargo with England, and muses that the French should be able to resolve the issue. A letter from Judah Paddock discusses being stuck in a hurricane.
      Ships Mentioned:Melancholy Intelligence,
    - Letters: S-Z, 1794 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including Valentine Swain, David Tallman, and an unknown correspondent. Most of the letters in this folder are in regards to either lack of payment by Alsop & Hicks or about late payments to Alsop & Hicks. The letter from the unknown correspondent is from Dunkirk and is completely in French. Other letters refer to mistakes in accounts and other financial issues. One letter discusses the "alarming progress of the fever" causing anxiety.
      Ships Mentioned: George
    - Letters: A-F; No-Name, 1795 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including an unnamed correspondent, John Alsop, and A. Coffin. It is at this time that John Alsop began retreating from New York City to Hudson, and is therefore writing to Hicks about how the business is faring, and his life in Hudson. This letter from Alsop appears to be more of a friendly letter than purely business correspondence. The letter from the unknown correspondent brazenly accuses Alsop & Hicks of being careless stating, "I was astonished at hearing that necessary care was not taken by you of the Ship C which Captain Swain left with you…." Other letters discuss an outbreak of smallpox that was moving through New York City, as well as the impact that the war between France and England had on shipping. This is also the first time that mentions of whale oil or spermaceti candles appear.
      Ships Mentioned:George
    - Letters: H-Z, 1795 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks from their clients, including Joseph Hussey. Most correspondence is in regards to normal business matters. A letter from Hussey discusses how the rigging broke on his ship, and he is requesting Alsop and Hicks send whatever they can in order to fix it, as he is trying to avoid condemning the ship.
      Ships Mentioned:Hope, John
    - Letters: A, 1796 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including John Alsop, John Alden, Alstorphius Von Hemirt, and Joseph Anthony. Correspondence is in regards to normal business matters, and there are occasionally hand written duplicates of correspondence, especially from Alstorphius Von Hemirt of Amsterdam.
      Ships Mentioned: Industry
    - Letters: B, 1796 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including Abe Barker and Barlow & Gorham. Correspondence is in regard to regular business matters.
    - Letters: C-Coates, 1796 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including John and Isaac Carroll, John Chapman, and Joseph Chase. Most correspondence is in regards to regular business matters. The correspondence from John and Isaac Carroll predominantly relate to their ship, Eliza, and her cargo. They also discussed the repairs that their ship desperately needed on her hull. John Chapman wrote a letter to Alsop & Hicks begging them to let him out of debtors prison because his children were sick and his wife could not survive without him.
      Ships Mentioned:Eliza,
    - Letters: Coffin, 1796 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from multiple individuals with the surname Coffin. In this folder is a letter in Dutch from an unknown correspondent. A letter from Alias Coffin discusses how British privateers are taking American sailors and ships in violation of current treaties. Most other correspondence is in regards to the sale of whale oil.
    - Letters: Constable-Cunningham, 1796 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including M. Constable, Joseph Cook Jr., and Daniel Crommelin & Sons. While most of the correspondence is in regards to business as usual, M. Constable writes to Hicks stating that 20 days was not enough time to load, unload, and ship the materials that Hicks requested to ship. Constable then informs Hicks that 40 days would be required.
      Ships Mentioned:Commerce,
  - Letters: 1796 D-P (Box -)
    - Letters: D-E, 1796 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including John H. Dayton, John Delano, and Killey Eldridge. Most of the correspondence is in regards to normal business matters.
    - Letters: F, 1796 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      This folder contains correspondence to Alsop & Hicks, Hicks & Doughty, and Hicks from their clients, including George Folger and Edward Forbes. The correspondence is in regards to regular business matters. In one letter Edward Forbes discusses how he has been waiting for the Revolution to come all week, but it has not yet arrived.
      Ships Mentioned:Polly, Juno
    - Letters: G-Heath, 1796 (Box 4, Folder 3)